Oury Family papers, 1799 - 1933
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Oury Family papers, 1799 - 1933
AZ 016
Smith, Cornelius Cole
Correspondence, diary, photographs, deeds, articles and speeches chiefly relating to Arizona territorial military experiences of Oury family members.
1 Linear Foot
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL:http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
The Oury family was an Arizona pioneer family, prominent in territorial political and military affairs. William S. Oury served as first Mayor of Tucson, 1864, and sheriff of Pima County, 1873-1877; he was a participant in the Camp Grant Massacre in which about 100 Aravaipa Apaches were killed. With Sylvester Mowry, he purchased the "Arizonian" newspaper of Tubac and moved it to Tucson. His brother, Granville Henderson Oury, served with the Confederate Army in the Civil War, and held various public offices including Arizona legislator, 1866, and U.S. congressman, 1880-1884. Gilbert Cole Smith, William Oury's son-in-law, was a U.S. Army officer who served as quartermaster for Fort Lowell, Tucson, Ariz. in the 1860s.
Organization
This collection is organized into five series.
Series I: William Sanders Oury, 1799 - 1885
Series II: Granville Oury, 1860 - 1864
Series III: Gilbert Cole Smith, 1862 - 1895,
Series IV: Cornelius Cole Smith, Jr., 1913 -
Series VI: Photographs, 1875 - 1927
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence, diary, photographs, deeds, articles and speeches chiefly relating to Arizona territorial military experiences of Oury family members. Includes William Oury's address to the Society of Arizona Pioneers, 1885, regarding the Camp Grant Massacre; and letters to his daughter relating events in Tucson, 1883-1885; as well as items pertaining to Granville Oury's Civil War service with the Confederate Army and a letter from Sylvester Mowry to Granville from an 1860 political convention. Gilbert C. Smith materials consist of his diary, 1857-1856; letters to relatives while serving with the California Volunteers in Arizona, 1862- 1863; a letterbook kept while at Fort Lowell. Photographs, chiefly of army officers, but also family members and Zuni Indians, 1862- 1894; military commissions; and annotated articles from "Frontier Times", 1928-1933. Also included are four photocopies of early land transactions involving George, August, and Wendell Oury in Virginia and Texas.
Most of this material appeared in William Sanders Oury: History- maker of the Southwest, by C.C. Smith, Jr., published by the University of Arizona Press, 1967.
Access Terms
Oury family -- Archives,
Oury, Mr. (Granville Henderson), 1825-1891.
Smith, Gilbert Cole, d. 1899.
Mowry, Sylvester, 1833-1871.
United States. Army -- Military life.
United States. Army. California Volunteers.
Confederate States of America. Army.
Apache Indians -- Wars -- History -- Sources.
Military bases -- Arizona -- History -- Sources.
Pioneers -- Arizona.
Camp Grant Massacre.
1800-1824.
1825-1849.
1850-1874.
1875-1899.
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.
Arizona -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.
Fort Lowell (Ariz.) -- History -- Sources.
Zuni (N.M.) -- History -- Sources.
Container List
- Series 1: William Sanders Oury, 1799 - 1885
  - Subseries 1: Legal Document, September 28, 1849
    - Land Deed,(photocopy), September 28, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 2: Correspondence, Outgoing, (William Sanders Oury to Lola Oury Smith), 1883 - 1885
    - November 29, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - September 8, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - October 18, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - November 15, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - February 22, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - May 13, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - November 20, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - December 24, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 3: Correspondence, Incoming, (Senah Oury to William Sanders Oury), 1864
    - May 17, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 4: Speech: "To the Society of Arizona Pioneers," 1885
    - "To the Society of Arizona Pioneers," April 6, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 5: Military Documentation, 1837 - 1838
    - Pay Voucher, (photocopy), June 14, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Pay Voucher,(photocopy), May 28, 1837 - January 4, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Auditor's Report, (photocopy), January 1838 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series 2: Granville Oury, 1860 - 1864 1860 - 1864
  - Subseries 1: Correspondence, Incoming, 1860
    - Incoming, (photocopy), April 22, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 2: Correspondence, Outgoing, 1863 - 1864
    - Outgoing, No Date (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Outgoing, No Date (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 3: Military Documentation, 1862 - 1863
    - "To The Public"-- an address to the citizens of Mesillia, Arizona, (photocopy), May 21, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Muster Roll-- Confederate States of America, (photocopy), May 21, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Resignation Petition-- Confederate States of America, (photocopy), February 24, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Severance Pay Voucher-- Confederate States of America, (photocopy), March 8, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Physical Description of Granville Oury-- Confederate States of America, (photocopy), October 8, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Oath of Allegiance"-- United States, (photocopy), October 8, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series 3: Gilbert Cole Smith, 1862 - 1895
  - Subseries 1: Correspondence, Outgoing, 1862 - 1863
    - July 4, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - August 21, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - March 27, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - April 18, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - June 23, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - July 20, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - July 26, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Outgoing, No date (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 2: Military Commendations, Commissions, "Personal Reports," Promotions, and "Letter Books," 1857 - 1895
    - Commendations-- United States. Army, July 5, 1871 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Commendations-- United States. Army, January 1, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Commission-- United States. Army, January 9, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Commission-- United States. Army, May 4, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Commission-- United States. Army, April 9, 1885 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Commission-- United States. Army, May 12, 1866 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Commission-- United States. Army, January 18, 1867 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Commission-- United States. Army, September 10, 1867 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Letters Sent Book," 1863 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "Letter Book, Tucson Depot"-- United States Army, July 1868 - February 1870 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - "Personal Report" or Diary-- United States Army, with accompanying Typescript, January 1857 - June 1867, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
    - Promotion-- United States. Army, May 16, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Subseries 3: Miscellaneous Documents, 1868 - 1883
    - Freemasonry-- Membership Certificate, June 17, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Marriage Certificate, July 1, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series 4: Cornelius Cole Smith, Jr. 1913 -
  - Subseries 1: Correspondence, Incoming, 1964
    - July 1964 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Subseries 2: Periodicals, 1927, 1928, 1930, 1933
    - "Frontier Times," 1927, 1928, 1930, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Subseries 3: Oury Family Land Transactions, 1780, 1799, 1823
    - (photocopies), 1780, 1799, 1823 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Series 6: Photographs, 1875 - 1927
  - Bell, J.M. (Major), 1922 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Cole, Cornelius (Senator), ca. 1922 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Crook, George (Brigadier General), ca. 1872 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Cusack, J.C. (Lieutenant), 1892 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Febeger (Admiral), ca. 1875 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Fish, Edward N. (Mrs.); Kerr, J.B. (Lieutenant); Nesmith, Mary D.; Smith, Gilbert Cole; Smith, Lola Oury, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Gregg, J.C. (Lieutenant), No Date (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Indian Runners-- Fort Wingate, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Lindsay, J.R. (Lieutenant), 1927 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Madden, John M. (Lieutenant), 1927 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Oury, Francis, ca. 1884 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Oury, Genevieve, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Oury, Genevieve, ca. 1884 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Oury, Granville, H., ca. 1862 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Oury, Granville, H., ca. 1880 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Oury, Inez Garcia, ca. 1890 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Oury, Malvina, ca. 1865 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Pershing, John J. (Captain); Evans, Bob (Captain), ca. 1904 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Poillon, Arthur (Lieutenant) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Smith, Cornelius C. (Colonel)-- "Regiment on Maneuvers," 1918 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Smith, Gilbert C. (Colonel), ca. 1900 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Smith, Lola Oury, ca. 1877 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Zuni Village, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Zuni Village-- "Indians Dancing," 1893 (Box 1, Folder 23)